<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  - 
  -  file:  manual.xml
  -->
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Network Comparison ToolKit Manual</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Michael</firstname>

      <surname>Smoot</surname>

      <othername role="mi">E</othername>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>

      <holder>University of California San Diego</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <sect1>
      <para>The Network Comparison Toolkit, or <emphasis>NCT</emphasis> was
      designed to be an extensible platform for comparing biological networks.
      The NCT is written in pure Java 1.5 and it now represents the canonical
      versions of the various algorithms used for comparisons. The NCT has its
      roots in the <ulink url="http://www.pathblast.org">PathBLAST</ulink>
      project and implementations of the underlying algorithims in C, Python,
      and Java. The motivation for the reimplementation of the algorithms is
      the development of software that is modular, easily maintained and
      easily extended for future research.</para>

      <para />
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>The Packages</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>graph</title>

      <para>The common currency of the NCT is the Graph interface. The
      interface defines how programmers should interact with graph objects.
      The Graph interface has several extensions that expand on the
      capabilities of a basic graph such as the KPartiteGraph which defines
      the methods used for interacting with k-partite graphs.</para>

      <para>Basic implementations of all the Graph interfaces have been
      provided. You obviously need to use concrete implementations of the
      graph objects, but whenever possible we strongly recommend that you code
      to the interface and not the class. For example: <programlisting>
// recommended usage
Graph&lt;String,Double&gt; g = new BasicGraph&lt;String,Double&gt;

// NOT recommended
BasicGraph&lt;String,Double&gt; g = new BasicGraph&lt;String,Double&gt;



// recommended method definition
public Graph&lt;String,Double&gt; getGraph();

// NOT recommended
public BasicGraph&lt;String,Double&gt; getGraph();
</programlisting> Coding to the interface provides flexibility to other users
      of your code to change underlying implementations without having to
      alter your code.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>graph.basic</title>

        <para>This package contains all of the implementations of the graph
        package interfaces. The implementations are not specific to
        networkblast, so could be used in other applications that require
        graph data structures.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>services</title>

      <para>The services package is comprised of several sub-packages. The
      intent of the package is isolate activities that are not core graph
      comparison duties in a separate package. Examples include the
      calculation of homology e-values between sequences, the creation of
      interaction graphs, the creation of synonym databases, access to
      sequence databases, and the like. In each case an interface is provided
      that defines how new software should interact with external
      services.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>filters</title>

      <para>The filter package provides a simple interface for filtering a
      collection of Graphs. Examples of the filters provided are the
      SortFilter and the DuplicateThresholdFilter. The SortFilter merely sorts
      a collection of Graphs based on the Graph's implementation of the
      Comparable interface. The DuplicateThresholdFilter filters out Graphs
      that have a certain percentage (the threshold) of nodes and edges in
      common.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>networkblast</title>

      <para>NetworkBlast, as the name suggests, is where the classes specific
      to the NetworkBlast/PathBlast algorithms reside. This package contains
      the CompatibilityGraph that represents the network alignment and the
      HomologyGraph used for calculating that alignment.</para>

      <para>Central to the NetworkBlast package is the NetworkBlast class
      itself. This class contains the main method that is called upon
      invocation of the networkblast program. The main method contains the
      actual code that reads the input, constructs the input graphs, defines
      the search and scoring classes used for the alignment, and shows how the
      output is generated. If there is any confusion about how certain classes
      relate to one another, a look at the main method might help clarify
      things.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>nct.networkblast.graph</title>

        <para>Contains the graphs specific to network blast such as the
        HomologyGraph and CompatibilityGraph. The HomologyGraph is a
        KPartiteGraph whose partitions are individual graphs and whose edges
        are homology relationships between nodes (proteins) between the
        partitions. The CompatibilityGraph</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>nct.networkblast.search</title>

        <para>Contains the search algorithms.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>nct.networkblast.score</title>

        <para>Contains the graph scoring algorithms.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>nct.networkblast.filter</title>

        <para>Contains a filter that is really only meaningful in the context
        of the NetworkBlast algorithm. However, the filter implements the
        Filter interface and would therefore be usable by any code needing a
        Filter. The results however, probably wouldn't have any
        meaning.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>