<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <body>

  <section name="About this Document">
    <p>
	    This document describes user functionality that will be built in Phase 1 of the 
	    Cytoscape Data Services project.  The focus of Phase 1 is to provide similar data
	    services functionality to that provided in Osprey.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section name="Feature #1:  Obtain Node Information from GRID">
    <P>
	    For each node in the graph, Cytoscape will download node information from GRID.
	    For each node, information will include:
	    <OL>
		<LI>ORF Name(s)</LI>
		<LI>Gene / Alias Name(s)</LI>	
		<LI>Description</LI>
	    	<LI>Gene Ontology Information
	    		<OL>
				<LI>GO Component</LI>
				<LI>GO Process</LI>
				<LI>GO Function</LI>
				<LI>GO Special</LI>
			</OL>
		</LI>
		</OL>
		All of this data will be displayed in a separate window.  Initially, data will 
		be presented in the same manner as currently used by Osprey (basically, a simple
		panel of tables and text boxes.)  In a later phase, we will redesign the data
	        presentation to follow the new Cytoscape look and feel guidelines.
	</P>
	<P>
		In Phase 1, the user will see one option under the Cytoscape PlugIn menu:
		<UL>
			<LI>Get Gene Information from GRID</LI>
		</UL>
	</P>
	<P>
		When the user selects this option, Cytoscape will download information about
		all nodes within the graph and cache the contents locally in memory.  Cytoscape
		will then pop-up a new "Gene Information" window.  When the user select
		an individual node, the Gene Information window will be updated to show the 
		selected node data.  If no node is selected, the window will not show any data.
    </P>
  </section>
  <section name="Feature 2:  Obtain additional interaction data from GRID">
	  <P>
		  Just like in Osprey, a user will be able to select a specific node, and 
		  then view node information within the "Gene Information" window.  Within
		  this window, we will include a "Get New Interactions" button.  
		  When the user clicks on this button, Cytoscape will connect to GRID, 
		  download a full list of interactions and display the list to the user.
		  The user can then add all of these interactions to the graph.
	  </P>
	  <P>
		  Again, for Phase 1, we will follow the design already provided by Osprey.
	  </P>
  </section>
  <section name="Technical Features">
	  <P>
		  This first phase of the project will follow the general guidelines put
		  forth in our Data Services Technical architecture document.
		  Phase 1 will therefore include:
		  First iteration of Cytoscape data services layer; and
		  Use of Java Caching System.
	  </P>
  </section>
  <section name="Schedule">
	  <P>
		  Phase 1 should take approximately two weeks of development.  Assuming 
		  we nail down user functionality by Wednesday, April 23, we can start real
		  coding on Thursday, April 24.  Phase 1 should therefore be complete by 
		  Friday, May 9.  This includes time to create unit test scripts via JUnit,
		  create a better Ant build process, and tweak the user interface.
	  </P>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
