<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <body>
	<section name="Detailed description of refactoring changes">
    	<p>
	    <pre>
Removed all action classes from CytoscapeWindow, placed in a new
directory called "actions". Each class constructor takes a
CytoscapeWindow as an argument, using that reference to access
everything it needs.  This should be changed to refer to the new
classes that replace CytoscapeWindow, and all of these classes
have no documentation or unitTests.

Rearranged remaining CytoscapeWindow methods for logical coherence,
into four main groups: (1) methods only called on initialization, or
when loading a new graph; (2) basic get/set methods for accessing data
members; (3) key action methods, like redrawGraph(); (4) various
utility methods that don't particularly need to be part of
CytoscapeWindow.

Rewrote almost all methods to access class data members indirectly
through the get methods; i.e. getGraphView().doSomething instead of
graphView.doSomething(). This allows pulling class members away into
different classes and redirecting the get methods.

Removed the network objects (graph, attributes, expression data) into
a CyNetwork object (unfortunately, Network is already a class
in cytoscape.visual, so creating another Network class would create
confusion. After all the plugins are rewritten to use CyNetwork
instead of cytoscape.visual.Network, we'll do a global search/replace
to rename CyNetwork back to just Network). CyNetwork lives in the
cytoscape.data package.

Removed the global objects (config, bioDataServer, etc.) to a Cytoscape
object. Cytoscape can be constructed with just a CytoscapeConfig
object, or with additional arguments specifying the other global
objects.

Removed all the window stuff to a CyWindow object. Most of the
CytoscapeWindow initialization and key action methods were moved too.
CyWindow lives in the cytoscape.view package.

Plugin loading remains in CytoscapeWindow, as there are many
different callers of the CytoscapeWindow constructor that expect
the constructor to trigger plugin loading.

Moved menu creation to a CytoscapeMenus class in cytoscape.view,
and moved CalculatorCatalog loading to a CalculatorCatalogFactory
class in cytoscape.visual. The former is called from CyWindow's
constructor, while the latter is called by Cytoscape's
constructor.

Moved the public debugLog member from CytoscapeWindow to CytoscapeConfig,
as CytoscapeConfig is the only class in all the core and plugins that
accesses this field.


Introduced an abstraction called NetworkView. This interface contains
the methods involved in displaying the network, while hiding the details
of the window and UI objects surrounding the view. The interface currently
contains the following methods:

CyNetwork getNetwork();
Graph2DView getGraphView();
VisualMappingManager getVizMapManager();

void setInteractivity(boolean newState);
void redrawGraph();
void redrawGraph(boolean doLayout, boolean applyAppearances);


other methods may be added as needed. This abstraction is useful since
many algorithms only need this set of methods. CyWindow is one class
that implements the NetowrkView interface.

Changed view/EditGraphMode, view/ReadOnlyGraphMode, and
browsers/NodeBrowsingMode to use this interface; the actual object
they refer to is a CyWindow instead of a CytoscapeWindow.

Changed dialogs/ShrinkExpandGraph and ShrinkExpandGraphUI to use
this interface.

	    </pre>
    	</p>
	</section>
  </body>
</document>


