<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <body>

  <section name="Cytoscape Tech Docs">
    <p>
	    Welcome to the Cytoscape Tech Docs Site.
	    This site was automatically generated via an open source tool, called Maven.
    </p>
    <P>Here's how to create/edit documents:
    <UL>
	<LI>Download and install the latest <A HREF="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven distribution</A>.</LI>
	<LI>In the main cytoscape cvs system, there is a new directory called cytodocs.
		Within cytodocs is a directory named xdocs -- all tech docs go in here.  All images 
		go in xdocs/images.
	</LI>
    <LI>Documents checked into cytodocs/xdocs need to conform to the XDocs format.  This is basically 
        a bare bones subset of XHTML.  Sample tags are available from the
        <A HREF="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/jakarta-site-tags.html">Jakarta Site.</A>  The only
        tricky part is to remember that all your docs need to be XHTML compliant -- most importantly,
	this means that every start tag, even &lt;P&gt; must have a corresponding end tag. 
	The easiest option to test for well-formedness is to load your XML document into 
	Internet Explorer -- if it renders, the document is well-formed;  otherwise, Explorer
	will display the specific error message.</LI>
	<LI>To add your document to the left-hand navigation bar, you need to modify 
		cytodocs/xdocs/navigation.xml.  Examples are already provided in the file.</LI>
	<LI>Once you are happy with your document, try previewing the document.  To do so, make sure Maven
		is installed correctly.  Then run:
<pre>
cd cytodocs
maven site:generate
</pre>
		This will automatically rebuild the whole tech docs site and place it in 
		cytodocs/target/docs/.  To preview the new site, open cytodocs/target/docs/index.html.
	</LI>
	<LI>Once you have previewed the site, and are happy with your new documents, email Ethan, and
		he will redeploy the site on the CBio site.  Obviously, we will work out something 
		more automatic in the future, but for low volume, this is fine.
	</LI>
    </UL>
    </P>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
